howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
this is a current episode currents are
shorter and less heavily produced than
our full-length episodes and generally
focus
on a single topic as always links to
books
articles and organizations mentioned are
available on the episode page at
jimrudshow.com that's jimrutshow.com
in this current episode we have on our
regularly returning guest john robb
who's got a
military background in the air force uh
and a key guy in building some of the
technology
that we use on the internet every day
and these days is a writer
about things strategic and
trend wise about what's going on in the
world
uh he's on patreon and i support him on
patreon i encourage everybody else too
as well for to support his important
work
under global gorillas uh and or john
robb on patreon
throw a few nickels in his dish we want
the boy to be able to eat
right as usual on the currents
on the currents episodes uh i basically
start with a single
artifact or statement or thing and then
spiral from there and
what caused me to reach out to john
today uh was
he ran a couple of tweets two or three
four i don't remember how many with
excerpts from an extraordinarily
interesting artifact
uh it's i would describe it as an
after-action report
on the uh siege and eventual capture and
burning of the third police precinct in
minneapolis
written at least nominally and it sort
of feels like it
by one of the participants and it's what
34 pages long
and uh quite remarkable uh explication
of uh kind of the dynamics that led to
them
being successful uh in the plan so
without him i'll turn it over to you
john and say what you would like about
that article and
and you know tease apart you know
strategy tactics that kind of stuff
yeah the one great thing about the way
protests are organized in the states
um is that we get a lot of feedback on
how things are organized
um people are you know constantly
writing about it tweeting about it
posting about it and this uh article is
pretty well written
and um it goes over the tactics and the
thinking associated with the protest
you know from an insider's perspective
somebody who is trying to escalate
the situation and um it goes over some
of the uh
core elements uh you know breaking uh
the protest into different
groups of expertise you know people who
focus on medical support people who scan
outside media or telegram or
airdrop to get information into the
protests and then back out
and then the uh the role of the peaceful
protesters the people who were
there to uh protest non-violently
who tend to be the the vast majority of
the people that they're
protesting he even uh you know talks
about how the looters fit into the whole
overall equation
so um the interesting thing is is the
way that
he thought about how they interacted one
thing in particular was
what he saw the reversal of the roles i
assume it's a he
might not be reversal of the roles of
between
non-violent protesters and the activists
are you know people who are
more kinetically focused uh in previous
protests in hong kong for instance the
kinetic protesters
were the ones who were protecting the
non-violent protesters from
police encroachment uh you know police
violence
uh being pushed back being
driven from the field and
in this protest due to the volume and
largely due to the nature of the protest
he didn't mention this because it is
about police violence
uh and that the police were put on it
into a defensive crouch
and were trying to de-escalate rather
than engage
on the whole in all of the thousands of
protests that went on
globally is that the non-violent
protesters were
extremely numerous and they were at the
forefront and that they
provided the cover for the
kinetic protesters usually people who
are uh
using ballistics meaning you know
throwing water bottles or
or rocks or or any kind of object at the
police to
you know prompt them into action and so
the non-violent protesters were the
shield because the police weren't
willing to
barrel into them and engage with them
and that created
an interesting dynamic in the sense that
the
kinetic protesters were able to force
the police
to widen their lines and engage in ways
that
ended up proving detrimental to their
overall strategic position
they looked like they were aggressing on
the non-violent protesters and that
caused
calls for de-escalation
in fact the third precinct itself was
was evacuated
because the politicians in in
minneapolis
wanted to de-escalate what they saw as a
confrontation between the peaceful
protesters and the police
um and that that created a new set of
opportunities for the way this protest
will
evolve over over the next few months
yeah quite
interesting as i was reading it you know
i'm a player of uh
war games typically turn-based or
quasi-turn-based
uh sometimes real-time uh computer-based
war games
and i i suspect the author may have been
as well because he essentially
calls out the various kinds of units it
reminded me of
playing total war medieval or something
right uh you know he talks about the
the non-violent folks but then he also
explicitly calls out the ballistics and
then he talks about the specialty units
the laser pointer people
and he goes into quite deep good detail
on how and when to use the laser
pointers
he talks about the fact that uh it's
important to have people on
uh police scanners listening to what the
police are doing
he goes into the details of
uh information security oh yeah we use
signal
because we know it's uh secure at least
secure enough
but we ought to be using uh on burner
phones so that the
stingrays i.e faults cell towers
operated by the police
uh can't get our personal information
and track us
uh so right this this was a person who
actually thinks about unit types and
uh and how the tactics combined with the
unit types
uh he also talks about how the looters
actually uh help by being a distraction
well on three levels he talks about it
you know being a distraction but also
providing supplies and also building
morale i mean
remind me of my clausewitz right uh as
we know at the end of the day according
to klausowitz the person who wins
is the one whose will breaks last right
and so
improving the the will and spirit of
your crowd the morale
uh is really important uh and so i
thought this to be a quite amazing quite
formal after action report uh
that to my mind painted a picture way
more detail than any i'd seen anywhere
else
you know i i think it's really a good
good report
well written covers all the angles does
some analysis
trying to you know determine lessons
learned from the engagement
is willing to learn willing to overturn
in
previously uh agreed upon tactics in
favor of stuff that works
you know trying to figure out how to use
laser pointers in in the
us context and that you know the dangers
of using a laser pointer is that you get
singled out by the police and hit with
rubber bullets or bullets that mark you
uh but if you're in a dense enough crowd
you can pull it off
or um if you want to drive away
helicopters
you have to have you know a concerted
effort by
many people in the protests uh acting at
once
um so there's lots of uh interesting
insight from somebody who's clearly been
on the ground
yeah my guess is this was not his first
uh ballistic
episode uh you know the level of
maturity of his analysis struck me like
this guy has been has done this before
right yeah and they you know he's even
talking about how they um
need to develop better ways of doing um
fact checking
in the field um that you know the same
kind of thing that we do online
when when you know we don't think as
individuals completely in terms of
verifying information anymore we rely on
our network to do it uh
is that when somebody comes forward with
a claim
like the national guard is 20 minutes
away or the
and they're marching towards us or the
uh
if we burn this facility down it'll
explode or that kind of thing
is that you have a large enough network
of people who actually verify
for you i mean give you the kind of
expertise give you the kind of insight
gather the information for you
so the crowd isn't herded
or panicked into action that will be
deleterious to their to their goals you
know it's
it's cool to see somebody uh engaged in
open source warfare thinking about how
all the pieces come together um and that
they're you know
more than just the uh different unit
types there's
people there with completely different
motives for being there
they talked a little bit about the
accelerationists the from the
on the right the boogaloo boys and then
you know how they
you know try to insert themselves into
the the early days of the protest
um but he doesn't really go deep in
to the different types of people that
are showing up at the protest with you
know
their different motivations so you know
beyond that
because i mean when people look at it
from the outside they they tend to think
of it
it has to be more than just you know
anti-racism
given the size and given the composition
of the crowds
um but the reason it still is
anti-racist in its
core form is that people are
in support of that and they're there in
large part because of motivations
that extend beyond that tired sick and
tired of the administration they're sick
and tired of all this
everything else that's going on in the
world and that this is it
something that's actually proven itself
capable of of
you know raising the large crowds
necessary to to immobilize a protest
yeah i think you're right that if the
signal comes from multiple sources i
mean while anti-racism
is the key and the core uh it's also i
think
very closely related to racism but not
the same thing by any means is the
you know tremendous increase in the
militarization of the police over the
last
40 years right uh you know i remember
being a kid
being a kid and being somewhat of a bad
boy and uh having my run-ins with the
police and i grew up in a place famous
for its vicious violent police at least
supposedly prince george's county uh
maryland
they're almost a watch word for bad
police but yeah though
they would cuff you upside the head if
you gave him any lip or lied to him
but but they were human and they'd cut
you some slack if you were polite and
reasonable
and they did not give off a militaristic
uh
vibe you know if you fuck with me at all
i will shoot your shoot you
dead uh and you know i think so much of
the
problems that come from policing in
general and
particularly in the uh you know black
majority neighborhoods is this
uh ratcheting up of militarization
uh you know even small cities now have
swat teams
uh you know it's just uh you know that i
think that really has pushed a lot of
people to be looking for some serious
systemic change
and you know the the the it seems at
first an idiotic
phrase defund the police or abolish the
police
probably has behind it uh you know a
realistic goal of let's
rethink policing why have we allowed
this
hyper-militarization hair trigger-ness
uh
to have increased and increased and
increased every year despite the fact
that
crime both crime overall and violent
crime has been on a massive decline for
30 years now right yeah um
there's four four times as many uh swat
teams now
as there were in 2001 i mean and all the
excess military equipment and all those
terrorist funds
uh anti-terror funds you know flowed
into police departments and they bought
this
equipment in bulk and hired a you know a
bunch of people who
did a lot of work doing counter
insurgency work in
in iraq and other in afghanistan you
know the the militarization of police
is probably the key point here is you
know maybe instead of defund places
you know demilitarize the police uh
maybe a
better on-point goal and you know also
you got to look at the
you know the the job itself it's
surprisingly you know when you look at
it you find that it's not a profession
even though it has a power of life and
death it's it's not you know
licensed and controlled like a
profession where
you know you have requirements for you
know training
the minimum standards as well as
continuous you have licensure you have
ethics standards you have an oath
and maybe this is regulated at the state
level
but the oversight of that should be done
by a professional organization that's
not a union
and it's not politicians it is not a
committee of
of civilians i mean it's something that
has an
kind of enduring investment in making
law enforcement a high quality activity
and if you do something that results in
an infraction of that
then you should lose your license to
actually practice law enforcement in the
state
potentially nationally so that kind of
self-policing
would you know instead of completely
defunding police and
is is to actually build it back up
another thing is that if you
look at the you start diving into the
kind of salary tables and a lot of you
you know universities have been
kind of pulling up on on state and local
employees you find that a lot of these
police departments pay these guys
extraordinarily well i mean
palo alto being the you know one of the
outliers but they're guys
pulling in with overtime 350 000 a year
and then he's not
those folks aren't unusual you know it's
police sergeant
350 000 a year so that's a lot of money
i don't care
whether it's california or not what this
suggests is that the
you know these organizations uh you know
become a lot
very self dealing and very protective
and unwilling to change
unwilling to you know adapt um
and that we may want to start thinking
about like charter uh precincts
like you know the privatization efforts
that where citizens have a lot more
control over who gets the contract
who doesn't um or um you know
cooperative law enforcement
probably a you know evolved model from
the community policing which focuses
more on the soft services
but um you know citizens who are willing
to step forward and spend time
and take the training and do the
training necessary to actually
police and to do it in a much more cost
effective way
as well as you know much more responsive
to the community but i don't hear any of
those suggestions
well i hear him i hear him floating
around uh you know there's a
couple of people put out long lists of
reforms that would make the police
more responsive and more responsible
including the professionalization idea
that you floated and one that went with
that
was a requirement just as it is a
requirement for
lawyers and doctors that they have
malpractice insurance
and then uh the insurance under
underwriters would have a substantial
amount of skin in the game
to make sure that they uh priced the
policies right you know so a cop that's
got
31 uh you know reports for excess of
violence uh you know his policy is 300
grand a year and
very quickly the uh the town says fuck
that this guy's out of here right
we can't we can't afford 300 000 a year
for it
uh and then the other one again you
mentioned in passing but again had a
total change
uh over the last 40 years are the
police unions who have unfortunately not
only worked for improvement of pay and
benefits but have been very instrumental
in developing
contractual methods to make it very very
difficult to even
investigate a crime by police i mean
typically the
oftentimes in big city police
departments that have strong unions
the contract literally says that uh it
has the force of law because it's with
the city itself
that the police cannot be questioned by
the prosecutors for
two to five days sometimes if the
officer interposes that right and those
of us know a little bit about the inside
baseball
policing uh therefore realized it was
quite a a smart tactical move in
minneapolis
for them to fire the police officers
which then uh made them not subject to
the union interposition of investigation
right so those things need to get uh
need to be gotten rid of i mean
you know i'm from a police family my dad
was a washington dc police officer for a
full career
and then he retired and then he went
back and did some federal law
enforcement my
younger brother was career federal law
enforcement one of my closest
first cousins was career police so i
understand the police perspective and i
do understand
that they need to protect have
protection to do their job and
to not be subject to vindictive citizens
i mean hell
every time you get a traffic ticket for
a borderline offense it's
very tempting to go make the police
officer's life hell
uh and police need to be protected from
that but on the other hand
you know to be able to force stall a
criminal investigation
for you know felony misconduct strikes
me as gross overreach uh
in the police unions and that needs to
be stopped yeah it's um
but it's really hard to reform anything
having to do with the
government employees and government
services there's just
too much stop energy available and they
try to you know when they
whatever that is true though our whole
system yeah whenever they put these
civilian commissions together
you know these blue ribbon panels or
whatever we've heard so many of these
had so many of these in the past they
they come and spend
18 months writing a report and by the
time a report comes out no one
no one listens to it the reforms don't
get instituted
nothing gets changed and and the panel
is disbanded and they go away
yeah so you know what what we need is
more uh take advantage of this
opportunity i mean
i i see these big you know consensus
actions these uh big you know
where the network pretty much agrees
that this is something we need to do
like
with the pandemic and then and then now
with police reform is that
you know we should take advantage of
these opportunities to get something
done
you know every one of these things is
like giving us a gift to say
in this area in this zone of focus
we have the ability to actually do some
meaningful reform
i mean you know we live in a you know a
cold war
superpower relic um really not well
fitted for the modern world it's
it's not adapting well and needs
reform and try out new things and and
and try to get some
new energy going and we're just
not and here's this mechanism for
actually making it possible where
er virtually everybody i mean 60 or so
agree 70
agree that we should go do some
something substantial in police reform
i mean for instance with the uh with
covid i mean
there are opportunities that presented
themselves like for instance
uh you know how do we stimulate an
economy where it's laying flat on his
back and we're still
kind of flat on our back well we think
new ways that we think in new ways maybe
emergency ubi or or something that can
get everybody spending all at once
give people the confidence to plan out
three or four or five months of spending
um in the future and and that gives them
the ability to
jolt this thing to life or um we can't
during the pandemic we couldn't build an
app
for helping us track it and and beat it
and continuously beat it
because we didn't trust companies and we
didn't trust the government we didn't
touch each other with data we had this
outdated model of privacy private data
versus a something that actually would
be dynamic enough to actually work like
a you know data ownership
you know where everybody owns their own
data and then the government rents it
for
a period of time in order to build an
app and make a app available to allow
us to be better prepared and and and
act as a unit against an external threat
like this
like like kobit was or is um
but you know we can't we're not making
any of the reforms and in large part we
can't even see them yet
so maybe it's going to take another
decade before
we start to see these threats as
opportunities and we start to see
you know the new ways necessary to
actually solve them
yeah maybe this time it'll be a little
different i don't know we'll see uh you
know the
minneapolis city council formally voting
to defund the police is kind of an
interesting
more than a thought experiment right uh
whether they actually go through with it
we'll see yeah i think as you know our
mutual friend
uh jordan hall just published a very
interesting essay on medium
uh titled defund and redesign everything
uh which you know
basically reinforces your point that
we're living with grossly
obsolete social operating systems and
maybe just maybe maybe maybe this point
is a tipping point where we are more
open than we've ever been before
uh to an effort to really look at each
of these things and say
yeah yeah you know uh one thing i think
we'll see out of this is that
in the near future is a return of
something akin to occupy
uh groups of protesters you know taking
over a
space in downtown sprawling over and
refusing to leave i mean the police
right now are in such a defensive crouch
and they're
you know a lot of the aggressive tactics
allowed them to throw people out
during the the occupy movement aren't
possible right now
um and that the occupation can serve as
a as a
as a good way to ensure that this
protest doesn't
completely die off and uh you saw a
little early example right now there's
what they call the capitol hill
autonomous zone in seattle which is an
early
early example of this i suspect we'll
probably see a lot of these
in many major cities um in terms of
defunding uh yeah it's going to be
interesting to see what happens as a
result of the defending effort like in
minneapolis
there's a hope that the community
policing
or you know maybe a new department
that arises out of the ashes will be
better than the one that they
had but a wholesale reform like that's
really tough and it tends to
not go well when you burn everything to
the ground and try to rebuild it
but um on the other hand uh if people
pull together they could probably do a
pretty good job of it so we'll see
see what happens though you know early
indicators are probably not that great i
mean
the uh did you see the video of the
interchange between the
mayor and uh the crowd when they were
you know putting the question to him you
know asking him whether or not he would
defund the police i did not
see it but i've heard like second or
third hand reports of it so
why don't you tell people what what
happened and what the implications are
yeah there was a
a large crowd um and some were up on a
podium
um the leaders yeah and the mayor
was by himself surrounded by the crowd
and you know it looked pretty imposing i
mean
you know he's probably you know pretty
uh scared when he was
was was being questioned and they said
okay we don't care about any of this
negotiation we just really want
to ask you one question will you defund
the police and he goes no
and then you know his cat calls and you
know the potential for him getting
getting attacked was really high uh they
kept on screaming at him and then they
opened up a corridor for him to walk
do a walk of shame out of the protest
you know it's very similar to what you'd
think would happen during the chinese
cultural revolution or you know
for someone even the game of thrones
kind of uh situation
so it's it's not i mean it's it was an
interesting dynamic and it doesn't
really
um point to a kind of a constructive
engagement to you know to reform the
police uh given a defending event
yeah that's uh that's about exactly what
i heard and i had the same
uh reaction this sounds an awful lot
like the early days of the cultural
revolution
uh and we remember where that ended up
right which is uh
uh very ugly uh you know so i i
i hope that people can take this moment
and be constructive but it may not play
out that way which
is something we should all keep our eye
out in terms of the branching of the
contingencies here as this unfolds
i want to go back a little a minute here
to your uh suggestion that
one of the things that may emerge from
the new environment
and the new sensibility of what's going
on is a resurgence of something like
occupy and put that back in the context
of this after action report on the third
precinct
do you think that the circumstances at
the third precinct were unique to that
situation
or do you think the uh you know the
tactics the
uh the unit types etc are more generally
applicable
to you know action in the streets uh
going forward
um well the specialization works um you
know specialization of roles
the fact checking works across protests
the dynamic between non-violent and
kinetic protesters that works
particularly in this context
particularly in the u.s how that it
plays into
something like an occupy effort is
pretty interesting because
if you surround yourself with
non-violent protesters in in a strategic
position
it then puts you in a position of being
able to bombard
everything that goes by um or keep up
pressure on a key building or a key
location either through fireworks and
lasers and bricks or catapults
like they did in hong kong um and that
it's incumbent upon the police to
actually try to remove it
remove that location and it puts them
into a situation where they're
confronting non-violent protesters
at least according to the media and
according to the way that things will be
portrayed and i mean the story here the
narrative here
um the pattern matching that's locking
this this view of the protest in places
is pretty inexorable it's hard to hard
to see it any other way
online at least for the moment and i
think the other one
as i was thinking about it while you
were talking about occupy
uh the other tactic that could easily be
adopted
is the one that the fellow in this paper
talks about
uh which is essentially taking advantage
of
uh raiders you know in this case in
minneapolis looters but one could
imagine imagine
occupy having flying squads that you
know head out and
and raise chaos two or three miles away
you know set 25
fires in 25 uh locations in various
places to
uh pull off the police at critical
moments to de you know to thin
their lines again you know this is
classic clausewitz right let's uh
or even the art of war guy right make
the guys spread out their lines
before you make your defi decisive move
you know let's say where you know this
occupy
is uh you know in front of goldman sachs
and their real goal is to
burn goldman sachs to the ground they
could use this uh
flying squad uh raider technique you
know not very
not dissimilar to what both sides did
during the american civil war
to you know make life more difficult for
the people confronting them yeah
it's it's um something that hong kong
protesters did too
so be everywhere was one of their their
mottos is that if you live far away from
the main protest site you can still
contribute by
doing things locally that would cause
the police to split apart and
respond to that diluting in particular
is
is kind of interesting in hong kong they
did it a little bit differently than
here
the protesters use it as a way to align
shops and businesses
to their cause if the company
was aligned with the chinese government
which the chinese government was trying
to force through
back channel means through legal means
if the company was aligned with china
they would vandalize the storefronts
whether it's a bank or whether it's a
big retailer and they would leave alone
the local businesses that supported
the protest so you'd go down the street
and you see
you know pristine storefront for stream
storefront and then vandalized bank
and in this protest it didn't seem i
mean the big box stores got hit
uh you know a lot of the big chains got
hit clearly they think that it was
aligned with the
system as is and there was a certain
amount of self-identification of stores
local stores locally owned places that
that tried to you know say that
we're separate we're different whether
it's black owned business or you know we
support the protests or
ways of indicating that they were
aligned with the uh with the protest
i thought it was kind of interesting
though in the days following the protest
you know when you in boston and in other
places um the local stores and local
restaurants that got hit hard
immediately turned around and said you
know even though they're standing on
in the ashes of their life's work is
that they're saying okay we support the
protests
granted it's genuine sentiment but it's
also a self-defensive measure they don't
want to
they don't want to get hurt or you know
again in the future they want to
you know align themselves with the crowd
and their potential customer base
yep extortion is a very old game right
the uh it was
it was the original business of the
mafia right and
we should expect that tactic to uh be
used as well because you know again the
thing i always tell everybody when one
group invents a new tactic or in this
case a system of tactics guess what
other sides maybe even their direct
antagonists are going to you know pick
and choose amongst those new tactics
and use them as well i mean you know the
nobody nobody gets a monopoly on coming
up with a new set of tactics it becomes
part of the common intellectual property
of humanity uh
unfortunately yeah it's unclear that
there's uh
much the police can do in order to
counter this that won't get them in
trouble in terms of
you know amplifying the violence or
responding to
these attacks uh de-escalation seems to
help a bit
you know accepting the uh taken
abandoning you know
kind of pledging support for the protest
uh seems to de-escalate they've used
that in iraq to
to de-escalate yeah i will say that some
of the a lot of the escalation seems to
be coming from the young
very uh thoughtful black lives matter
people who've you know gone on the media
and said hey we don't want this to be
violent you
outside assholes uh stop doing that and
it
basically has at least for the time
being stopped and so there is some moral
uh authority i think that has been
helpful in the least the later stages in
the final de-escalation or at least the
current the escalation i don't want to
say final yet we'll see
what happens well there's a there's a
definitely a struggle between the uh
the non-violent core of the protests and
the uh kinetic
groups and and the fact that even in the
article we're uh discussing earlier
he had to mention that that if you are
engaged in kinetics that you have to do
it as a group because if you're
a lone person throwing a water bottle
uh or water bottles or rocks or whatever
the non-violent
enforcers will come grab you and eject
you or
isolate you and deal with you in a way
that
ejects you from the protest so um
the group actually protects them against
those enforcers from
uh actually uh imposing their will on
the on how the protest is conducted
amazing amazing i think on that note
we're going to end it this has been
a wonderful uh dive into
you know sort of really thinking through
what's going on and what new tactics are
evolving and thinking through possible
implications of that so again john i
want to thank you for being here
oh thanks jim it's fine
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared janes consulting
music by tom muller at modern space
music dot com